This video is sponsored by Proton Mail.
It's been a while since I made my last
video about the Ukraine war, but recent
events have prompted me to do a new one.
With Republicans back in power in the
US, the equation has changed quite a
bit. Or did it? What are the outlooks
for Ukraine in this war going on for
three and a half years at this point?
Will Russia ever run out of hardware and
men? These are some of the questions
I'll be trying to answer in a neat
organized presentation style. First,
let's take a look at the current
situation on the front line. Chances are
you haven't heard news of large
battlefield movements or the taking or
retaking of cities. And that's because
not much has been happening on the front
line lately. At least not much new. So
far in 2025, Russia has managed to take
over a couple thousand square kilometers
distributed mostly evenly along the
massive front line. While that does
sound like a lot, remember that the
internationally recognized territories
of Ukraine make up around 603,000
kilometers. So at this rate, Russia will
conquer the full territory of Ukraine in
about two centuries. A further point to
consider here is that Russia is pressing
forward at such a glacial pace in areas
that are mostly flat and open. No
mountains, no blockby-block urban
warfare, just flat open fields where
current advances are measured in
villages and tree lines. Additionally,
the more time passes, the more time
Ukrainians will have to build and
strengthen defensive lines. So if Russia
can barely advance now on relatively
easy terrain, how would they fare on the
difficult terrain? But let's imagine a
scenario where somehow Ukrainian
defensive lines collapse in the east and
Russia takes over the entire territory.
Well, congratulations. Now you only need
to take over large cities like Hark,
Zaporia, Nippro, and Paba in addition to
having to cross a large river and a
swamp area. Or you can try pushing
forward south of Harkiv by which you'll
have shrunk the front line to half
allowing Ukrainians to concentrate their
defenses. Then, if you manage to break
through those defenses, your reward will
be a blockby-block urban warfare in
multiple cities with pre-war sizes
ranging between 300,000 and 1.4 million.
And once you're done with that, you'll
have taken over 1/3 of Ukraine. But
could Russia somehow get a second wind,
accumulating men and hardware, and just
go for it after all? With that, let's
talk about the Russian and Ukrainian
capacity to sustain the war. Though much
of the information here is a state
secret, we are still able to get a rough
picture of what's happening. But just
like how it's important to keep
sensitive military data secure, you
should do the same with your private
correspondents. This is where today's
sponsor, Proton Mail, comes in. Proton
Mail is a privacy focused end-to-end
encrypted email service made to keep
your personal data safe from
unauthorized eyes. It is now as relevant
as ever, as governments around the world
are getting increasingly comfortable
with surveilling their own citizens.
This is also a reminder that the Trump
admin controls both the NSA and the FBI
and a law called Section 702, allowing
them to surveil even foreigners. But
they also use that same law to spy on US
citizens. Who would have thought?
Needless to say, the rule of law is
increasingly an afterthought here. So,
it's best to keep your private
correspondence private. And Proton Mail
was made for exactly that, both for
personal and business use. I also use it
as my personal private email. If you
already have an email address at one of
the big providers like Gmail, switching
is easy as you can set up Proton's
autoforwarding feature in just a few
clicks. Go to proton.me/adam
something to get started with Proton
Mail for free. Their service is always
free with optional paid subscription
plans for additional features and
benefits. That's proton.me/adam
something. Thank you for checking out
Proton Mail. When it comes to the side's
ability to sustain the war, we must take
into account two factors, hardware and
manpower with the note that both have to
be available for a military to function.
You can have a million men, but if you
can't equip them, you can't really use
them. Or you can have a million tanks,
but if you can't man them, they're just
inert hunks of metal. In terms of
manpower, Ukraine still has significant
resources. The draft age has not been
lowered below 25, meaning if the need
arises, they can train and equip
hundreds of thousands more. They want to
avoid this for now since it's not a
great idea to lose your youngest adult
generation in a war, especially in a
country with serious population decline.
Another factor helping Ukraine here is
that they are on the defensive, which
generally means less casualties in
addition to fighting a war for their
existence. So, if push comes to shove, a
lot more people would pick up arms if
need be. Also, Ukraine's heavy reliance
on FPV drones does seem to compensate
for manpower shortages since now if you
want to clear a trench, a building, or
if you want to stop advancing Russian
infantry instead of sending out 30
dudes, you can just fly a few dozen FPV
drones at them from a distance. So, all
in all, the Ukrainian manpower situation
is not great, but not terrible either.
Russia, on the other hand, is
increasingly in a difficult situation.
In September 2022, Putuchin attempted a
partial mobilization which resulted in
hundreds of thousands fleeing the
country and the situation threatened
with an actual public backlash. Russian
society is thoroughly atomized and low
trust enough so that most people don't
mind the meat grinder in Ukraine
swallowing more and more of their fellow
countrymen. However, the moment they get
involved personally against their will,
like through mobilization, that seems to
constitute the red line for most.
Therefore, Putin is keen on exhausting
every single other option before even
considering another mobilization. And so
their methods have been very creative.
The army recruited in prisons, homeless
shelters, impoverished regions with high
joblessness and has been trying hard to
push conscripts into the battlefield
despite it being illegal. The new method
according to the system of research
project is to recruit people as
volunteers, basically as mercenaries
whose contracts do not automatically
renew at the end of a year service or
less, as opposed to regular military
contracts that automatically renew until
the end of the war. So, the non-renewing
contract is used to lure people in who
are on the fence, who are enticed by the
pay, but are turned off by the
indefinite contract. But this also has a
side effect. Apparently, such soldiers
are treated as second rate. If a
Ukrainian defensive position needs to be
stormed in a so-called meat assault,
guess who's going in first. And in one
of such mercenary programs, the one that
promises the most flexibility, you
basically operate in a legal gray zone
and do not have access to any support
like rehabilitation or a pension after
your service. This of course puts a
heavy toll on your population, leaving
thousands of working age men by their
roadside disabled and traumatized. But
for Russia, this seems to be the high
cost of mening their formations without
a mobilization. So both Russia and
Ukraine are holding on for now in terms
of manpower and are trying not to cross
their red lines, mobilizing below the
age of 25 for Ukraine and a general
mobilization for Russia. If both were to
happen though, Russia would be at a far
greater risk of backlash while Ukraine
is kept relatively safe from it due to
fighting a defensive war. With that in
mind, let's take a look at hardware.
Russia has been churning out missiles
and drones at a very high rate and has
launched about 20,000 at Ukraine this
year. In terms of surface hardware,
however, the situation is not looking
great. What we're mostly looking for
here are tanks and other AFVS. And
according to Covert Cabal's numbers
based on satellite images, Russian tanks
at storage bases are down from about
6,100 in 2022 to about half, 3,300 in
2024. Meanwhile, AFVS are down from
around 7,400 to about 4,000. So, both
categories pretty much have. What Covert
Cabal additionally points out, however,
is if we subtract vehicles in a terrible
state, so ones that look like scrap even
from orbit, the number of tanks and AFBs
in storage both crater to about 1,000
each. And this is after adjusting for
vehicles that might have been unseen
inside garages. So, it's not looking
good for Russia, like at all. So, when
will they run out, one might ask? Well,
in warfare, there is no such thing as
running out, so to speak, because Russia
also produces new vehicles, sometimes by
using the Rex at storage bases. It's
much slower and more work intensive than
just reactivation. But they are doing
it. And there is also new production
from scratch, like T90M tanks, which
research by the Conflict intelligence
team puts it around 300 per year. But
since Russia has been losing about 1,000
tanks per year, that just won't cut it,
it seems. So, there will always be a
flow of vehicles to the front lines.
Only when the storage is empty out, this
flow will be much smaller. There will
likely never come a point where we stop
seeing Russian armored vehicles on the
battlefield, but their numbers will
gradually decline over time as stoages
empty out. That means Russia will not be
able to fight at the same pace as it did
so far, potentially giving Ukrainians
opportunities to hit back. With that,
what about Ukraine? In terms of AFBs and
tanks, they are doing decently. Of
course, they could always use more, but
they have already gotten plenty of
hardware with a lot still in the
pipeline. According to Orics, the
confirmed minimum number of deliveries
are 81 aircraft, 71 helicopters, 914
tanks, 101 AFVS, 1,157 IFVs, 3,856
APCs, 1540 MREs, 6,870 IMVs, 410 toad
artillery, 600 SPGs, and various other
hardware. And yet to be delivered as of
now are 41 aircraft, 25 helicopters, 142
tanks, about 60 AFVS, 8001 APCs, 300
MRAPs, 1240 IMVs, 35 total artillery,
194 SPGs, and others. I chose to
highlight these numbers to show that
Ukraine has received and still is
receiving robust support from allies and
will not run out of equipment anytime
soon. I would also like to note that the
vast majority of equipment is not
cutting edge western stuff. It's usually
30 to 40 years old or even older used
hardware. much of it Soviet made.
Another important thing to remember is
that NATO countries are increasing their
military spending massively, which will
likely free up additional used hardware
for Ukraine to use. So, Ukraine will be
reasonably well supplied for the
foreseeable future, except in one area,
air defense. Ukraine currently operates
eight Patriot batteries. According to
Zeninski, they would need about 25.
Russian ballistic missiles continue to
be a severe threat against which
Patriots excel. But to put that number
of 25 into perspective, there are 186
Patriots in the world in total. There is
also the bottleneck of missiles. Against
planes, PE 2 missiles are enough, which
are also produced in Europe. However,
against ballistic missiles, you need the
PAC 3, which is only produced by the US
at a rate of about 600 per year. And
Ukraine is not the only one standing in
line for them. Also, US support for
Ukraine continues to be in question. For
a brief period, the US halted
deliveries, saying they had to review
their stocks. This is at the end of a
long line of anti-Ukraine sentiment,
including calling Zilinsky a dictator
and the infamous Oval Office meeting.
But just a few days ago, Trump seems to
have taken a complete 180 and is now
fully in support of Ukraine. Apparently,
this is good news. But this also means
that the US can't really be relied on.
After all, what if Trump changes his
mind again? These shifts by the Trump
admin are, in my opinion, due to three
factions within and their struggles. the
old hawkish neoonservatives who are
driven by geopolitical and business
considerations versus the new Christian
fascist isolationist wing who are driven
by their sympathy towards Vladimir Putin
and hate towards the western quote
unquote liberal world which Ukraine is a
part of according to them. And in the
middle there is Trump, the face and
legitimizing force of the administration
who just likes it when people clap at
him. He wants to make deals, score quick
wins, peace agreements and so on. And
the administration will generally tip
towards the position he holds which at
the moment is pro- Ukraine. But what if
Trump capitulated to the isolationists
and cut off all aid permanently? Not
only that, but even sales. I don't think
even such a step would cause Ukraine to
collapse. Ukraine also has its own
production, for example, of its own SPGs
and IMVs in addition to 2 million FPV
drones and 2.5 million shells per year.
So even if all aid seized Ukraine
completely, it still wouldn't mean that
Russia would get a free ticket for
stomping Ukraine. So this is the
situation we are currently at. a slow
grind along the front lines while seeing
the count of casualties and destroyed
hardware go up until one of the sides
can no longer keep up. Aside from that,
there are also potential black swan
events which might change the situation
completely. These include Ukraine
getting to missiles and destroying the
carriage bridge, for example, or some
unforeseen internal conflict within
Russia. The point is things will
continue on like this until they don't.
So, for now, the best thing we can do is
to keep track of events and of course
elect pro- Ukraine leaders in the West
in the meantime. With that, I thank you
for watching and I'll be seeing you next
time.